Guide to the Jack Waters Papers MSS.111
Fales Library and Special Collections
Jack Waters Papers
1979-2016
Fales Library and Special Collections
Waters, Jack
MSS.111
3 Linear Feet in one record carton, one manuscript box, and one flat box.
3 film reels
The Jack Waters Papers contains information pertaining to downtown performance artist, filmmaker, writer, media activist and choreographer Jack Waters. The collection contains film elements from the 2001 preservation of three of his films under the supervision of Waters, the Fales Library, Jon Gartenberg, BB Optics, and the Estate Project for Artists With AIDS. In addition, the Jack Waters Papers contain a number of paper files pertaining to his various projects, such as writings, articles, and work with film festivals.
Biographical Note
Jack Waters is a filmmaker, performance artist, choreographer and writer who has been active on New York's Lower East Side performance and art scene for over twenty years. In 1979, Waters received his BFA in Dance from Julliard College in New York City. That same year, he choreographed a performance called Personifications for Alvin Ailey's American Dance Theater. Over the next few years, Waters would go on to choreograph numerous shows for the ADT, such as Echo and Narcissus (1980), Form and Meaning (1984-1986), and Apres Minuit d'Une Faune (1983). In 1981, Waters co-founded POOL, a choreographer's collective that also created films, music, multimedia works, site-specific installations, and other exhibitions both in New York and around the world. POOL has performed and exhibited at the Kitchen, the Franklin Furnace, Creative Time, the Pyramid, La Mama, and Rote Fabric (Zurich), to name but a few spaces. Concurrently, Waters became the events coordinator for a great many performance spaces in downtown NYC, such as Area, The Saint, the Pyramid Club, Danceteria, and Limelight, in addition to clubs and venues in other cities such as Miami and Hamburg, Germany.
Waters, along with his partner Peter Cramer, undertook the first of their many collaborative projects together in 1982 when they co-founded Allied Productions, Inc., a not-for-profit multipurpose media/arts organzation. Allied Productions, Inc.'s goal was to foster a sense of community through artistic sponsorship, and to that end supported both individual and collective artistic efforts in every conceivable medium. Under the blanket of Allied Productions, Waters has produced, distributed, and exhibited films, both his and others', in a variety of venues. In 1983, Waters and Cramer also became the co-directors of the ABC No Rio art space on the Lower East Side. Their first exhibition together was the "Seven Days of Creation" show, with each day devoted to the work of a specific artist. Waters and Cramer emphasized community-building in their tenure as No Rio's co-directors (which lasted until 1988), working with public schools and settlement houses in the neighborhood to provide arts instruction for Lower East Side denizens.
In 1985, Waters and Leslie Lowe co-founded Naked Eye Cinema, an ABC No Rio-based film venue dedicated to showcasing challenging work by new filmmakers such as Todd Haynes, Jon Moritsugu, Christine Vachon, Kembra Pfahler, Nick Zedd, Todd Verow, and Cassandra Stark, among many others, beside the likes of Sergei Eisenstein, Maya Deren, and the Maysles Brothers. Naked Eye Cinema devoted itself to exhibiting both film and video in a number of galleries, salons, and nightclubs in addition to ABC No Rio. Under the combined auspices of ABC No Rio, Allied Productions, and POOL, Waters and Cramer organized and produced a number of national and international events and exhibitions.
In 1984, Waters began shooting his first film, Berlin/NY (1984-1986), which was initially used as a backdrop to one of Waters' dance performances. The film documented the similiarities between post-WWII Berlin's collapsed ruins and a pre-gentrified Lower East Side in the 1980's. Among Waters' many other film projects are The Ring Our Way (1987-1992), an ambitious multi-part retelling of Wagner's Ring Cycle that fleshes out the original work's queer subtext; Diotima (1991), which is, in Waters' own words, "a cinematic essay on the pornography debate" that incorporates the contrasting opinions of "Schopenhauer, Dworkin, and the opinions of the cast"; The Male Gayze (1990), a film concerned with "perception, observation, and erotic description"; The Flower Market (1993), a fictionalized video about the homoerotic underpinnings of New York City flower shops; Percodan and Wisdom (1995), a video tribute to the NYC piers; Introducing Mr. Diana (1996), a video portrait of underground zine artist Mike Diana; Remnants (1997), a multi-screen projection event that incorporated live performance, film, video, and slide projection which originally premiered at the Mix Festival in NYC; and Short History/No Memory (2000), a digital video documentary that traces the history of queer and AIDS activism. Waters' films have exhibited in festivals and other venues in New York, such as the Anthology Film Archives, the Millennium Film Workshop, ABC No Rio, the Collective for Living Cinema, and the Cantor Film Center. Additionally, his films have been exhibited in Los Angeles, Canada, Switzerland, Germany, and France. In 2000, three of Waters' films - Diotima, The Male Gayze, and Berlin/NY - were selected for preservation by the Estates Project for Artists With AIDS, in conjunction with Jon Gartenberg, BB Optics, and the Fales Library at New York University for an ongoing preservation project of works by HIV+ film- and videomakers.
Waters has consistently been involved in dance for the past two decades as well, either starring in or choreographing his and other people's works. The dance segments of The Ring Our Way and Remnants have been performed in various venues around New York City, and he has additionally co-authored Black and White Study (1999) with Peter Cramer. He has collaborated with Kembra Pfahler, Nicola, and Jackie Kaye in various dance projects as well. Through Allied Productions, Waters and Cramer launched the Dancetube project in 2001, an experimental performance/plastic art group that uses group expression and public performance to foster social activism and for which Waters directed the theatrical extravaganza Il Spettacolo Provolone (2003).
Over the years, Waters has been affiliated with such arts groups as Collaborative Projects, Inc. (Colab), the Millennium Film Workshop, Film/Video Arts, the American Film Institute, and the New York State Council of the Arts' Visual Arts Program. He has contributed articles on a number of topics, ranging from politics to sexuality to dance, to a great number of publications, including Poz, Fuse, Jumpcut, Lesbian and Gay New York, the New York Blade, the Movement Research Journal, and was a contributing founding writer of the Color Life news journal. Waters has served on numerous committees, including programming and selection work for the Mix Festival (1999-2000) and speaking on panels presented by the Franklin Furnace and the Estate Project for Artists With AIDS (both 2000). Waters continues to be active in the performance scene today and still lives and works on the Lower East Side.
Scope and Contents
The Jack Waters Papers largely consists of materials relating to Waters' film projects, namely Diotima, The Male Gayze, and Berlin/NY. Among these materials are shooting scripts, original elements and preservation master materials of the films, and audiocassette soundtracks. The collection also contains information about some of Waters' other projects, such as his work with the Mix Festival and various writings and criticism. Additionally, the Jack Waters Papers contains several folders of research and biographical materials pertaining to an article Waters wrote in January 2000 about performance artist Valerie Caris.
Arrangement
The Jack Waters Papers are arranged into two series: Series I: Files and Series II: Film and Audio. Each series is divided into several subseries.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jack Waters, 2001.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact NYU Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Related Materials
Jay Blotcher Papers.
Dennis Cooper Papers.
Jaime Davidovich Collection.
The Downtown Flyers and Invitations Collection.
Guerrilla TV Archive.
Sarah G. Jacobson Papers.
Alan Klein Papers.
The Mix Collection.
Heather Lewis Papers.
Michelangelo Signorile Papers.
David Wojnarowicz Papers.
Experimental films -- United States; Performance art.; Homosexuality and motion pictures.; AIDS (Disease) and the arts; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); Audiocassettes.; Film materials.; Caris, Valerie; Cramer, Peter Francis; ABC No Rio (New York, N.Y.); MIX NYC; Naked Eye Cinema; Allied Productions Inc.; BB Optics; Charas/El Bohio Community Center
- Series I: Files, 1981-2000
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the paper files donated to Fales by Jack Waters, and includes draft articles; research on Valerie Caris; shooting scripts, technical information, and financial documents relating to Waters's films; and project files from the Mix Festival.
  Arrangement
  This series is divided into five subseries: Subseries A: Selected Writings; Subseries B: Notes/Materials; Subseries C: Valerie Caris; Subseries D: Films; and Subseries E: Other Projects.
  - Subseries A: Selected Writings, 1982-2000
    This subseries consists of some of Jack Waters' writings for various publications, including articles and drafts thereof.
    - Selected writings and notes - Anna Sokolow, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Selected writings and notes - "Performance on the Lower East Side", circa 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Selected writings and notes - "Seven Days of Creation", 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Selected writings and notes - The Male Gayze, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Selected writings and notes - Appearance in Barbara Hammer's Nitrate Kisses, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Selected writings and notes - Hilton Als critique, circa 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Selected writings and notes - misc., 1993-2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries B: Biographical Notes/Materials, 1996-1997
    This subseries consists of notes and materials pertaining to Waters' life and works, such as reviews of his works, teaching applications and resumes.
    - Career overview (contains news clippings, reviews, resumes/performance history), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Teaching applications, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Subseries C: Valerie Caris, 1981-2000
    This subseries contains materials pertaining to an article Jack Waters wrote for Poz Magazine on performance artist Valerie Caris, such as articles, biographical materials, writings, and general information about her artwork and performances.
    - Poz article - "Portrait of the Artist as a Sex Bomb", 2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Poz article - Draft of article, "Blood Fairy", undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Poz article - Drafts and notes for article, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Poz article - Notes for article, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Poz article - Draft of article with annotations by Caris, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Poz article - Financial documents, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Poz article - Correspondence and notes, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Poz article - Interview and notes, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Research - Biographical facts, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Research - Caris' projects - Women's Caucus for Art National Conference, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Research - Caris' projects - The Contessa's Contract, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Research - Caris' projects - Queen Sex Positive, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Research - Caris' projects - Milton Art Museum: "Art and Caring: From the Inside Out", 1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Research - Caris' projects - Midwest Popular Culture Association performance and panel, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Research - Caris' projects - Institute of Contemporary Art show, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Research - Caris' projects - Misc., undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Research - Press clippings, reviews, 1979-1998 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Research - Photos, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Research - Press clippings and photos, 1994-1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Research - Reviews, bio, resume, 1981-1998 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Subseries D: Films, 1991-1992
    This subseries contains paper files pertaining to Waters' films, Diotima, and The Male Gayze. Among these paper files are shooting scripts and drafts, technical information, and financial documents relating to the films.
    - Diotima - Technical, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Diotima - Technical, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Diotima - Fundraising, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Diotima - Editing, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Diotima - Fiscal, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - The Male Gayze - reviews, technical info, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Subseries E: Other Projects, 1995-1999
    This subseries contains documents relating to Waters' work with the Mix Festival as a member of the programming committee. There is also a folder with documents pertaining to Waters' and Peter Cramer's organized hunger strike against the auctioning off of the Charas/El Bohio community center on the Lower East Side.
    - Mix Festival - 1995 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Mix Festival - 1999, programming committee (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Charas/El Bohio - Hunger strike info, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Series II: Film and Audio, 1984-2000
  This series contains all of the elements from three of Jack Waters' films, Diotima, The Male Gayze, and Berlin/NY.
  This series is divided into three subseries: Subseries A: Original Elements; Subseries B: Preservation Master Materials; and Subseries C: Access Copies.
  - Subseries A: Original Elements, 1984-1991
    This subseries consists of the original film and audio materials Waters donated to the Fales Library for preservation purposes, and includes 16mm negatives, reel-to-reel audio tape, audiocassettes, and Super 8 film. There is no reseracher access to this material.
    - Berlin/NY - Original, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 111.0013)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Credit info: Jack Waters
      Gauge: Super 8mm
      Footage count: [225 feet]
      Extent: 1/1
    - Berlin/NY, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0015)
      Format: Audiocassette
      Capacity: 90 minutes
    - Male Gayze - Original, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 111.0016)
      Gauge: 16mm
      Footage count: 397 feet
    - Male Gayze - Master, 1990-02-14 (Box 2, Folder 111.0031)
      Credit info: "Jack Waters/Ed Bair/Bear Tracks Studio "
      Format: 1/4 in. reel to reel
      Capacity: [400 feet]
    - Diotima Serial #6 - Negative Roll #1, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0020)
      Credit info: "Jack Waters/Allied Prod. "
      Footage count: [200 feet]
      Extent: 1/4
    - Diotima Serial #6 - Negative Roll #2, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0021)
      Footage count: [100 feet]
      Extent: 2/4
    - Diotima Serial #6 - Negative Roll #3, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0022)
      Extent: 3/4
    - Diotima Serial #6 - Negative Roll #4, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0023)
      Footage count: [150 feet]
      Extent: 4/4
    - Diotima Serial #7 - Negative Roll #5, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0024)
      Footage count: [75 feet]
      Extent: 1/3
    - Diotima Serial #7 - Negative Roll #6, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0025)
      Extent: 2/3
    - Diotima Serial #7 - Negative Roll #7, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0026)
      Extent: 3/3
    - Diotima Serial #8 - Negative Roll #8, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0027)
      Footage count: [250 feet]
      Extent: 1/2
    - Diotima Serial #8 - Negative Roll #9, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0028)
      Extent: 2/2
    - Diotima Serial #10 - - Negative Roll #10, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0029)
      Footage count: [05 feet]
    - Diotima - Roll #2 (Positive) [Serial #10], undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0030)
      Footage count: 155 feet
    - Diotima Serial #11, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0018)
      Capacity: [600 feet]
    - Diotima Serial #14, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0032)
    - Diotima Serial #15, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0033)
    - Diotima Serial #16, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0034)
      Credit info: Jack Waters/Beartracks
    - Diotima Serial #17, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0035)
    - Diotima Serial #18 + 19, 1991-09-13 (Box 2, Folder 111.0036)
    - Diotima Serial #76, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0037)
      Capacity: 30 minutes
  - Subseries B: Preservation Master Materials, 2000
    This subseries contains materials used to assemble the composite prints of Waters's films, such as internegatives, interpositives, sound tracks and workprints. There is no reseracher access to this material.
    - Diotima - A Wind Interpositive (Pix Only), 2000 (Box 2, Folder 111.0004)
      Footage count: 1056 feet
    - Diotima - B Wind Dupe Negative, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 111.0005)
    - Diotima - B Wind Optical Track, 2000-06-28 (Box 2, Folder 111.0006)
    - Diotima - A Roll Internegative, 2000-06-30 (Box 2, Folder 111.0007)
    - Diotima - B Roll Internegative, 2000-06-30 (Box 2, Folder 111.0008)
    - Diotima - Workprint, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0019)
      Footage count: 1021 feet
    - Berlin/NY - S/S Pic Internegative, 2000-06-30 (Box 2, Folder 111.0009)
      Footage count: 540 feet
    - Berlin/NY - Optical Track, 2000-06-30 (Box 2, Folder 111.0010)
    - Berlin/NY - Silent Workprint From Internegative, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0014)
      Footage count: 517 feet
    - Male Gayze - S/S Pic Internegative, 2000-06-30 (Box 2, Folder 111.0011)
      Footage count: 458 feet
    - Male Gayze - Optical Track, 2000-06-13 (Box 2, Folder 111.0012)
      Footage count: 458 ft.
    - Male Gayze - Workprint From Internegative, undated (Box 2, Folder 111.0017)
      Footage count: 434 feet
  - Subseries C: Access Copies, 1984-1993
    This subseries contains 16mm composite prints of the preserved films Diotima, The Male Gayze, and Berlin/NY. These copies are available for researcher use. Contact the Fales archivist for further information.
    - Diotima, 1993 (Reel 111.0001)
      Gauge: 16mm, color, sound
      Footage count: 1039 feet
    - The Male Gayze, 1990 (Reel 111.0002)
      Footage count: 440 feet
    - Berlin/NY, 1984 (Reel 111.0003)
      Gauge: 16mm, color/black and white, sound
      Footage count: 525 feet